RG 019, Department of Social Services
Connecticut State Library
Department of Social Services records
1809-1960
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Dept. of Social Services
9.5 cubic feet
The Department of Social Services provides a broad range of services to the elderly, persons with disabilities, families, and individuals who need assistance in maintaining or achieving their full potential for self-direction, self-reliance and independent living.
RG019
Multiple
Historical Note
The Department of Social Services provides assistance to families and individuals through programs such as child-care block grants, energy assistance, vocational rehabilitation, refugee assistance, programs for the elderly, temporary assistance for needy families, food stamps, Section 8 housing vouchers, and the state child support enforcement plan. The Department has evolved through several titles that reflect the changes in public policy toward those citizens in need: State Board of Charities was established in 1873; name changed to Commission on Public Welfare in 1919; in 1921 name changed to Department of Public Welfare; 1935, name changed to Public Welfare Council; Office of the Commissioner of Public Welfare was established in 1935; 1953, name changed to State Welfare Department and the Welfare Commissioner; 1975, name changed to Department of Social Services; in 1979 Social Services split in two. The direct successor agency is the Department of Income Maintenance, which retains the same Commissioner and Statutory authority as Social Services. The other is the Department of Human Resources. In 1993 the Department of Social Services reformed by merger of: Department of Income Maintenance, Department of Human Resources, and Department on Aging.
See also the.
Scope and Content
Series 1. State Board of Charities contain letter books, 1883-1901, and registers of state paupers accounts that predate the board, 1809-1824 and ledgers created by the Board and subsequent agencies, 1877-1917. Series 2. Public Welfare Council contains one report to the General Assembly, 1947. Series 3. Welfare Department contains minutes of meetings of the boards through the public welfare council, 1893-1951; a secretary's diary, 1893-1922; several reports and a Master's thesis, and records of the Litchfield County Temporary Home, 1908-1915; and the New Haven County Temporary Home, 1899-1890, 1910-1916.
Arrangement
Series 1. State Board of Charities, 1809-1917, 5.5 cubic feet
Letterbooks, 1883-1909, Accession: 1972-001, 3 cubic feet (10 volumes)
Pauper Accounts, 1809-1917, Accession: T000754, 2.5 cubic feet (8 volumes)
Series 2. Public Welfare Council, 1947, Accession: 2002-021, 1 folder
Series 3. Welfare Department, 1893-1960, Accession: 1972-002, 4 cubic feet
Related Material
RG 008 Office of the State Comptroller for pauper records.
RG 061 County Governments for temporary home records.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Board of Charities; Connecticut. Dept. of Social Services; Connecticut. Public Welfare Council; Connecticut. State Welfare Dept.
Subjects:
Charities -- Connecticut; Children -- Institutional care -- Connecticut; Connecticut. Board of Charities -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut. Dept. of Social Services -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut. Public Welfare Council -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut. State Welfare Dept. -- Records and correspondence; Public welfare -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Account books; Correspondence; Minutes; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. State Board of Charities, 1809-1917; 5.5 cubic feet
  - Letterbooks, 1883-1909; 1972-001; 3 cubic feet (10 volumes)
    - 1883 May 18-1883 December 11, 1 volume (Volume Unnumbered volume)
    - 1885 September 1-1897 April 12, 1 volume (Volume Volume 1)
    - 1897 April 15-1898 May 9, 1 volume (Volume Volume 2)
    - 1898 May 13-1899 April 18, 1 volume (Volume Volume 3)
    - 1899 April 21-1900 April 2, 1 volume (Volume Volume 4)
    - 1900 April 3-1902 January 24, 1 volume (Volume Volume 5)
    - 1902 January 24-1903 July 30, 1 volume (Volume Volume 6)
    - 1903 August 3-1905 May 10, 1 volume (Volume Volume 7)
    - 1905 May 10-1907 August 8, 1 volume (Volume Volume 8)
    - 1907 August 10-1909 May 13, 1 volume (Volume Volume 9)
  - Pauper Accounts, 1809-1917; T000754; 2.5 cubic feet (8 volumes)
    - 1809-1815, 1 volume (Volume Item 1)
      Book in reverse contains a list of payments by the State of Connecticut to the "Port of New London" and the "Coast Guards" for the support and maintenance of troops and fortifications at New London, Stonington and Groton, Oct. 1775 - Jan. 1777.
    - 1815-1824, 1 volume (Volume Item 2)
    - 1877-1883, 1 volume (Volume Item 3)
    - 1883-1887, 1 volume (Volume Item 4)
    - 1887-1896, 1 volume (Volume Item 5)
    - 1897-1906, 1 volume (Volume Item 6)
    - 1906-1910, 1 volume (Volume Item 7)
    - 1910-1917, 1 volume (Volume Item 8)
- Series 2. Public Welfare Council, 1947; 2002-021; 1 folder
  - Collections for care in state mental institutions in Connecticut, 1947; 1 folder
    Report to the 1947 General Assembly by the Public Welfare Council
- Series 3. Welfare Department, 1893-1960; 1972-002; 4 cubic feet
  - Minutes, 1893-1951; 23 volumes
    - 1893 July 19-1897 April 6, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1897 May 1-1900 August, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1900 September-1902 September, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1902 October 1-1910 June 30, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1910 July 1-1914 September 30, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1914 October 1-1918 September 30, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1918 October 1-1921 July 1, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1921 July 1-1923 June 30, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1923 July 1-1925 June 30, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1925 July 1-1927 June 30, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1927 June 29-1928 December 19, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1928 December 26-1930 June 4, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1930 June 25-1931 December 16, 1 volume (Box 2)
    - 1932 January 4-1932 December 28, 1 volume (Box 2)
    - 1933 January 3-1933 December 7, 1 volume (Box 2)
    - 1933 December 27-1934 December 27, 1 volume (Box 2)
    - 1935 January 3-1935 June 28, 1 volume (Box 2)
    - 1935 July 28-1937 June 24, 1 volume (Box 2)
    - 1937 July 1-1939 February 23, 1 volume (Box 2)
    - 1939 September 11-1942 June 17, 1 volume (Box 2)
    - 1942 June 24-1945 June 19, 1 volume (Box 3)
    - 1945 July 18-1948 June 17, 1 volume (Box 3)
    - 1948 September 8-1951 May 23, 1 volume (Box 3)
  - Minutes of Special Meetings, 1921-1928; 2 volumes (Box 3)
    Reverse chronological order
    - 1921-1925, 1 volume (Box 3)
    - 1925-1928, 1 volume (Box 3)
  - Minutes of Supervisors' Meetings, 1935-1945 (bulk 1935-1937); 1 volume (Box 3)
  - Secretary's Diary, 1893 July 19-1922 July 1; 5 volumes (Box 3)
    - 1893 July 19-1898 September 30, 1 volume (Box 3)
    - 1898 October 1-1903 October 1, 1 volume (Box 3)
    - 1903 October 1-1910 June 30, 1 volume (Box 3)
    - 1910 July 1-1918 September 30, 1 volume (Box 3)
    - 1918 October 1-1922 July 1, 1 volume (Box 3)
  - Management Study of Welfare Administration in Connecticut, circa 1933; 1 volume (Box 3)
  - Emergency Relief Commission Report, 1935; 1 volume (Box 4)
  - Special Report on Relief and Reemployment, 1938; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - "Corrected" Annual Report of the Public Welfare Council, 1946; 1 binder (Box 4)
  - Reference Materials, 1933-1960 (Box 4)
    - Organization, structure, and legislation on the Welfare Department, 1933-1953 (Box 4)
    - Services for Indians (Box 4)
    - Public foster care for dependent and neglected children in Connecticut (Box 4)
    - Child Welfare (Box 4)
    - Report of Governor's Committee on Welfare Legislation, 1938 December 16 (Box 4)
  - Litchfield County Temporary Home, Board of Management Meeting Records, 1908 January-1915 October; 1 volume (Box 5)
  - New Haven County Temporary Home, 1889-1916; 2 volumes (Box 5)
    - Record Book, 1889-1890; 1 volume (Box 5)
      Record book (labelled "Volume 7") contains secretary's diary, notes, correspondence, etc.
    - Minutes, 1910-1916; 1 volume (Box 5)